Guide to the New-York Historical Society General Correspondence 1805-2024 (bulk, 1805-1982) NYHS-RG 2
New-York Historical Society
New-York Historical Society general correspondence
1805-2024 (bulk, 1805-1982)
New-York Historical Society
NYHS-RG 2
152.63 Linear feet in 360 boxes and 7 oversize folders.
The New-York Historical Society general correspondence record group contains chronologically arranged communications directed to and from the institution and its officers. The bulk of correspondence through the early twentieth century is incoming only, though some notes, responses, and letterpress copybooks (1876-1911) of outgoing correspondence appear. Carbon copies of outgoing correspondence commonly appear after the early twentieth century. The files are predominated by requests for reference assistance; research reports; inquiries pertaining to membership and library operations; proposals of materials for donation, sale, or transfer; arrangements for lectures, events, and publications; acceptances of election to member or officer positions; financial transactions; requests for material exchanges; and invitations, circulars, and other printed matter generated by N-YHS and outside institutions. Correspondents include N-YHS officers, prominent historians, politicians, writers and lecturers, scientists, genealogists, artists, printers and booksellers, and colleagues from libraries, societies, government agencies, and other organizations.
Related Materials
This finding aid relates to just one record group of the New-York Historical Society archives. Although this record group includes the bulk of correspondence incoming to N-YHS throughout its history until 1982, significant correspondence on specific topics to that time can be found in several other N-YHS record groups. Post-1982 correspondence is also found in other record groups. For information about the other record groups and for overall information about the archives, please see the overview Guide to the New-York Historical Society Archives (NYHS Archives).
Scope and Contents Note
The New-York Historical Society general correspondence record group contains the chronologically arranged central files of communications directed to and from the institution and its officers. These files range over almost all of N-YHS's first two hundred years of existence, from its first full year of operations in 1805 to the end of Director James Heslin's administration in 1982, though files from 1960 forward are currently restricted. In addition, the record group includes a series of selected letters from notable correspondents that ranges to 2017.
For the nineteenth century, the bulk of correspondence is incoming, but some notes, responses, and letterpress copybooks (1876-1911), of outgoing mail appear. Most communication is written or directed to the Librarian, as well as other officers. The copybooks and yearly registers of correspondents, beginning in 1876 when N-YHS appears to have formalized a system for retention of correspondence, may serve as a guide to researchers in locating materials related to specific individuals and organizations and these continue through 1908. By the early twentieth century, carbon copies of outgoing correspondence appear regularly and continues through 1982.
The record group is predominated by requests for reference assistance; research reports; inquiries pertaining to membership and library operations; proposals of materials for donation, sale, or transfer; arrangements for lectures, events, and publications; acceptances of election to member or officer positions; requests for exchanges of material, such as annual reports or other publications; and invitations, circulars, and other printed matter generated by N-YHS and outside institutions.
Internally produced correspondence includes memoranda such as meeting minutes excerpts, official acceptances and resignations, drafts and notes for deceased member memorials, presentation and resolution drafts, and informal reports on relevant legislation, commissions, funding, finances and investments, acquisitions and donations, buildings maintenance and facilities, and other aspects and issues of operations.
Correspondents include N-YHS officers, prominent historians, politicians, writers and lecturers, scientists, genealogists, artists, printers and booksellers, publishers, donors, antiquarians, and colleagues from libraries, museums, societies, government agencies, and other organizations. International repositories and individuals, many of whom are honorary N-YHS members, correspond from distant locations including China, France, Portugal, Brazil, and Denmark.
Arrangement
The New-York Historical Society General Correspondence (NYHS-RG 2) record group is organized in five series:
Series I. Notable Correspondents (1805-2017)
Series II. Letterpress Copybooks (1876-1911)
Series III. General Correspondence (1805-1908)
Series IV. General Correspondence (1908-1982) (Restricted for 1960 and later years)
Series V. Topical Correspondence (1917-1985)
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Most correspondence files dating from 1960 and later are generally restricted until 2033; see Series IV.
Acquisitions (Libraries) -- New York (State) -- New York.; Associations, institutions, etc. -- Membership -- New York (State) -- New York.; Buildings -- Design and construction.; Centennial celebrations, etc. -- New York (State) -- New York.; Education -- New York (State) -- New York.; Genealogists -- Correspondence.; Historians -- Correspondence.; Historic buildings -- Conservation and restoration.; Historic sites -- United States.; Learned institutions and societies -- New York (State) -- New York.; Librarians -- Correspondence.; Museums -- Acquisitions -- New York (State) -- New York.; World War, 1939-1945 -- War work -- Red Cross.; New York (N.Y.) -- History -- Societies, etc.; New York (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs.; Architectural drawings (visual works); Bookplates.; Lectures.; Letters (correspondence); Heslin, James J. (James Joseph), 1916-1999 -- Correspondence; Moore, George Henry, 1823-1892 -- Correspondence; Stevens, John Austin, 1827-1910 -- Correspondence; Vail, R. W. G. (Robert William Glenroie), 1890-1966 -- Correspondence; Wall, Alexander J. -- Correspondence; New-York Historical Society -- Archives; New-York Historical Society -- Correspondence
- Series I. Notable Correspondents, 1805-2024; 0.42 Linear feet in one document box
  Arrangement Note
  The series is arranged in chronological order.
  Scope and Contents Note
  The Notable Correspondents series consists of letters removed from the General Correspondence files (see Series III) by prior N-YHS staff based on their perceived value and importance. Correspondents include former American presidents and significant scholars, authors, politicans, journalists, historians, and other figures.
  A bulk of the letters are acknowledgments of election as an Honorary Member or responses to invitations to deliver a lecture or attend an N-YHS event. The content for every letter in this series is noted in the container list, with the exception of three files arranged and described based on common event or correspondent.
  Highlights of the series include correspondence documenting the N-YHS acquisition of John Jay Audubon's original Birds of America watercolor portfolios from his widow Lucy and a letter from Thomas Jefferson Randolph discussing the condition of Thomas Jefferson during the year leading up to his death. Substantive manuscripts include an account by John R. Bartlett of his mid-19th-century travels through Mexico, the American Southwest, and California; report by Amos Kendall on the death of Tecumseh; extrapolation by Orasmus Holmes Marshall of research into the site of La Salle's 1679 shipyard; and contestations by George Gibbs of recent claims on the island discoveries of Christopher Columbus.
  - N-YHS to John Henry, 1805-1806 (Box 66, Folder 1)
    Constitution sent with notice of election as a member of N-YHS.
  - Samuel L. Mitchill to John Pintard, 1807 May 25 (Box 66, Folder 1)
    Note accompanying donation of public and original national documents, praising Pintard's ability to gather, preserve, and arrange.
  - F.B. Winthrop to Samuel Miller, 1809 June 30 (Box 66, Folder 1)
    Inventory of 21 historical books dated 1609-1725 and a 1630 manuscript of "A Modell of Christian Charity, written on Board the Ship Arrabella by John Winthrop" sent to Miller.
  - M.S. Willets(?) to John Pintard, 1809 September 2 (Box 66, Folder 1)
    Acceptance of invitation to dine at N-YHS and attend with ladies a lecture of Dr. Miller.
  - Academy of Arts to N-YHS, 1809 September (Box 66, Folder 1)
    Copy of resolution appropriating the North East Room of the second story of the Government House to N-YHS and its amendment changing the locale to the North West Room.
  - Representative of Samuel L. Mitchill to John Pintard, 1809 October 16 (Box 66, Folder 1)
    Inventory of coins and metallic tokens donated by Mitchill to N-YHS.
  - Toasts, circa 1804-1809 (Box 66, Folder 1)
    Draft of toasts for delivery at unspecified N-YHS function.
  - Gouverneur Morris to John Pintard, 1810 January 27 (Box 66, Folder 2)
    Acceptance of election to First-Vice President of N-YHS.
  - DeWitt Clinton to John Pintard, 1810 March 22 (Box 66, Folder 2)
    Report of the passage of the bill for endowment of N-YHS in the New York Senate.
  - C.C. Moore(?) to John Pintard, 1813 July 22 (Box 66, Folder 2)
    Declaration of intention to send books to N-YHS.
  - Thomas Jefferson to John Pintard, 1814 January 9 (Box 66, Folder 2)
    Acknowledgment of election as Honorary Member of N-YHS.
  - John Quincy Adams to Samuel Miller, 1814 July 31 (Box 66, Folder 2)
  - Lewis, Rogers for John Pintard to Ogden Hoffman, 1821 April (Box 66, Folder 3)
    Receipt for payment of annual dues.
  - John Quincy Adams to David Hosack, 1826 July 26 (Box 66, Folder 3)
    Acknowledgment of N-YHS resolutions to honor the memory of John Adams and Thomas Jefferson.
  - [Thomas Jefferson] Randolph to David Hosack, 1826 August 13 (Box 66, Folder 3)
    Acknowledgment from Monticello of condolences for the death of Thomas Jefferson and personal account of Jefferson's health deterioration over the final year of his life.
  - Edward P. Livingston to John Delafield, 1828 November 27 (Box 66, Folder 3)
    Acknowledgment of receipt of N-YHS circular and inquiry into its probable indication that Delafield has been elected a member of N-YHS.
  - Charles Carroll of Carrollton to N-YHS, 1829 January 19 (Box 66, Folder 3)
  - Isaiah Thomas to James Swords, 1830 June 22 (Box 66, Folder 4)
    Expression of appreciation for Swords' donation to American Antiquarian Society and discussion of health problems.
  - M. Thomas to N-YHS, 1831 May 24 (Box 66, Folder 4)
    Executor of the estate of Isaiah Thomas informing N-YHS of a $300 bequest.
  - John Delafield to Executor of the Will of the Late Isaiah Thomas, 1832 March 27 (Box 66, Folder 4)
    Follow-up to Isaiah Thomas estate regarding the bequest to N-YHS.
  - Chris C. Baldwin to James Swords, 1832 April 19 (Box 66, Folder 4)
    Request to N-YHS for use of its influence in the American Antiquarian Society's attempts to develop their historic newspaper collection.
  - Levi Lincoln to Robert Sedgwick, 1833 September 21 (Box 66, Folder 4)
    Letter of introduction for Chris C. Baldwin, Librarian of the Antiquarian Society.
  - Edward Everett to John C. Jay, 1839 March 16 (Box 66, Folder 4)
  - John Quincy Adams to N-YHS Committee on Lectures, 1839 February 23 (Box 66, Folder 4)
    Decline of invitation to present series of lectures at N-YHS due to busy schedule.
  - John Quincy Adams to Joseph Blunt, 1839 April 13 (Box 66, Folder 4)
    Inquiry into the time and other logistics of Adams's April 30 lecture at N-YHS. A notation in the folder indicates this letter was presented to N-YHS by B.H. Field on March 4, 1884.
  - Henry Clay to N-YHS, 1839 April 22 (Box 66, Folder 4)
    Decline of invitation to attend the N-YHS celebration of the 50th Anniversary of the Inauguration of George Washington due to distance.
  - Edward Everett to N-YHS, 1839 April 24 (Box 66, Folder 4)
    Decline of invitation to attend the N-YHS celebration of the 50th Anniversary of the Inauguration of George Washington due to competing obligations.
  - Martin Van Buren to N-YHS, 1839 April 26 (Box 66, Folder 4)
  - John Quincy Adams to John C. Jay, 1839 May 7 (Box 66, Folder 4)
    Note accompanying submitted manuscript of discourse delivered at the N-YHS celebration of the 50th Anniversary of the Inauguration of George Washington.
  - George Bancroft to Frederic De Peyster, 1839 July 6 (Box 66, Folder 4)
    Acknowledgment of election as Member of N-YHS. Asks if the N-YHS library will accept a work of his in American history.
  - John Tyler to Frederick De Peyster, 1842 February 25 (Box 66, Folder 5A)
  - Letters of Watson and Cochrane Relating to the Journals of the British House of Commons, 1843, 1844 (Box 66, Folder 5B)
    Includes two letters commenting on the 16 volume set dating from 1650 to 1676, with gaps, held by N-YHS. These letters were formerly held in the Miscellaneous Manuscripts collection. They were transfered to the N-YHS institutional archive correspondence record group in 2016.
  - John Jay to John Wakefield Francis, 1844 November 1 (Box 66, Folder 5A)
    Printed invitation to November 5, 1844 meeting of N-YHS.
  - Albert Gallatin to E.H. Benedict, 1844 November 2 (Box 66, Folder 5A)
    Report on circular invitations sent; recipients listed include Hon. John Pickering and George Ord of the American Philosophical Society. [typescript only; note to see original IN ARCHIVES]
  - Millard Fillmore to Erastus C. Benedict, 1844 November 13 (Box 66, Folder 5A)
    Decline of invitation to attend the N-YHS 40th Anniversary celebration due to competing obligations.
  - John Quincy Adams to Erastus C. Benedict, 1844 November 12 (Box 66, Folder 5A)
    Acceptance of invitation to attend the N-YHS 40th Anniversary celebration.
  - Martin Van Buren to Albert Gallatin & His Associates of the Executive Committee, 1844 November 15 (Box 66, Folder 5A)
    Decline of invitation to attend the N-YHS 40th Anniversary celebration.
  - John Quincy Adams to Albert Gallatin, 1845 March 17 (Box 66, Folder 5A)
    Note accompanying James Fenimore Cooper commemorative medal, presented to N-YHS on behalf of Commodore Jesse D. Elliott.
  - Henry O'Reilly to Prosper M. Wetmore, 1845 May 4 (Box 66, Folder 5A)
    Acknowledgment of election as Corresponding Member of N-YHS (under the new regulations); detailed description of O'Reilly's private scholarship on the history and westward expansion of New York since the Revolutionary period, and his manuscript collection assembled in support thereof, which he believes of interest to N-YHS.
  - Henry Clay to John Jay, 1845 May 7 (Box 66, Folder 5A)
    Response to the N-YHS report on the country's adoption of a new national name.
  - Albert Gallatin to John Jay, 1846 July 15 (Box 66, Folder 5A)
    Note accompanying letter from Charles J. Smith and his transmitted copy of General Nathaniel Woodhull's journal of General Amherst's expedition in 1760. [typescript only; note to see original IN ARCHIVES]
  - John F.W. Herschel to Albert Gallatin, 1846 December 10 (Box 66, Folder 5A)
  - Martin Van Buren to John Russell Bartlett, 1847 September 15 (Box 66, Folder 5A)
    Acknowledgment of an unnamed honor (likley Honorary Membership) bestowed by N-YHS.
  - Martin Van Buren to John Jay, 1849 June 20 (Box 66, Folder 5A)
    Decline of invitation to special meeting of N-YHS following the death of Andrew Jackson.
  - Zachary Taylor to Luther Bradish, 1849 May 17 (Box 66, Folder 6)
  - Zachary Taylor membership certificate, 1849 April 3 (Box 66, Folder 6)
    Signed by all N-YHS officials.
  - Benson J. Lossing to George H. Moore, 1851 January 2 (Box 66, Folder 7)
    Introductory letter and accompanying notes on the surrender of General Burgoyne.
  - Benson J. Lossing to George H. Moore, 1851 April 1 (Box 66, Folder 7)
    Descriptive note accompanying three Revolutionary War relics to be presented for inspection by N-YHS members at upcoming meeting.
  - Henry R. Schoolcraft to N-YHS, 1851 October 3 (Box 66, Folder 7)
    Introductory note accompanying extensive August 20, 1850 letter from Amos Kendall on the death of Tecumseh.
  - Jared Sparks to George H. Moore, 1852 March 16 (Box 66, Folder 7)
    Decline of invitation to deliver lecture at N-YHS due to poor health.
  - John R. Bartlett to "dear Friend", 1832 [1852?] May 20 (Box 66, Folder 7)
    Extensive dispatch from San Diego, recounting Bartlett's travels through Mexico, southwestern America, and California; details his study of indigenous languages and interviews with native tribes about mistreatment by white settlers and invaders. The letter appears to be dated 1832, but notations on an enclosed typescript indicate prior readers have taken it to be 1852 because of references to the discovery of gold.
  - Ogden Hoffman to Frederic De Peyster, 1852 June 9 (Box 66, Folder 7)
    Letter accompanying donation of papers of Lieutenant Governor Cadwallader Colden to N-YHS.
  - William Gilmore Simms to Rev. Francis L. Hawks, 1852 October 8 (Box 66, Folder 7)
    Decline of invitation to deliver lecture at N-YHS.
  - Edward Everett to Augustus Schell and George H. Moore, 1852 October 14 (Box 66, Folder 7)
    Confirmation of lecture to be delivered at N-YHS on December 2.
  - Edward Everett to Augustus Schell and George H. Moore, 1852 November 1 (Box 66, Folder 7)
    Request to postpone December 2 lecture at N-YHS until the adjournment of Congress.
  - Ephraim George Squier to George Moore, 1852 November 10 (Box 66, Folder 7)
    Confirms to Moore the subject of his upcoming paper on hieroglyphics of Mexico and Central America.
  - Hamilton Fish to George H. Moore, 1852 November 30 (Box 66, Folder 7)
    Note accompanying donation of eight volumes of the American Archives published by order of Congress.
  - James Buchanan to Augustus Schell and George H. Moore, 1852 December 31 (Box 66, Folder 7)
  - Orsamus Holmes Marshall to George H. Moore, 1853 May 25 (Box 66, Folder 7)
    Introductory note and manuscript detailing Marshall's investigation into the site of La Salle's shipyard, settled in 1679 for the construction of Le Griffon; hand-drawn map also included.
  - Lyman C. Draper to George H. Moore, 1854 March 2 (Box 66, Folder 7)
    Request from Wisconsin Historical Society for N-YHS publications.
  - Donald Grant Mitchell to George Moore, 1854 January 24 (Box 66, Folder 7)
    Update on Mitchell's progress on a lecture to be delivered at N-YHS, tentatively titled "How to Look at Pictures."
  - William H. Seward to Luther Bradish, George Bancroft & Others, 1854 October 21 (Box 66, Folder 7)
    Decline of invitation to attend N-YHS 50th Anniversary celebration due to competing obligations.
  - George Grote to Andrew Warner, 1854 November 2 (Box 66, Folder 7)
  - James Buchanan to N-YHS, 1854 October 31 (Box 66, Folder 7)
    Confirmation of distribution of unspecified materials sent from N-YHS to their designated recipients.
  - William Gilmore Simms to Luther Bradish, 1854 November 9 (Box 66, Folder 7)
    Decline of invitation to attend N-YHS 50th Anniversary celebration, offering high praise to N-YHS.
  - William Cullen Bryant to John Romeyn Brodhead, 1854 November 14 (Box 66, Folder 7)
    Decline of invitation to write ode for N-YHS 50th Anniversary celebration.
  - Winfield Scott to Luther Bradish, 1854 November 15 (Box 66, Folder 7)
  - Edward Everett to George H. Moore, 1854 November 17 (Box 66, Folder 7)
    Decline of invitation to attend N-YHS 50th Anniversary celebration due to competing obligations; includes reflection on the past half-century of American history.
  - Fitz-Greene Halleck to George H. Moore, 1854 November 22 (Box 66, Folder 7)
    Decline of invitation to attend N-YHS 50th Anniversary celebration.
  - Edward Everett to Luther Bradish, 1856 March 8 (Box 66, Folder 8)
    Acknowledgment of receipt of invitation to repeat lecture on the character of George Washington.
  - John Jay to N-YHS, 1857 October 15 (Box 66, Folder 8)
    Description of the house in Lower Salem, or Lewisboro, Winchester County, where British spy Major John Andre was confined following his capture and wrote a famous letter to George Washington, and of which Jay has prevented the destruction and hopes N-YHS will assume the preservation.
  - John Gibson to E. Ferry [Terry?], 1857 November 5 (Box 66, Folder 8)
    Assemblage of copies of letters, news clippings, resolutions, and research excerpts relating to movement to honor the late sculptor Thomas Crawford through a bronze cast of his famous Indian statue. The original letters were dated 1857, but these are copies, possibly from 1879 or later.
  - Fitz-Greene Halleck to Samuel Osgood, 1858 January 20 (Box 66, Folder 8)
    Expression of gratitude to N-YHS for unspecified favor.
  - George Morris to George H. Moore, 1858 April 15 (Box 66, Folder 8)
    Provision of the issue numbers for the Home Journal.
  - George Gibbs to George H. Moore, 1858 April 20 (Box 66, Folder 8)
    Introductory letter and accompanying manuscript contesting claims that Columbus discovered Watling's Island and Cat Island; copy of letter to claimant, author of Landfall of Columbus, Captain A.B. Becher R.N.; original letter to Moore lists original drawings and survey of Grand Turk Island by George Judson Gibbs as enclosed.
  - Fitz-Greene Halleck to Andrew Warner, 1858 May 17 (Box 66, Folder 8)
    Decline of invitation to dinner.
  - Rich Varrick De Witt to Frederic de Peyster, 1858 October 28 (Box 66, Folder 8)
    Letter accompanying transmittal of watercolor of Fulton's original experimental steamboat The Clermont, which navigated the North River, including extensive description and sketches as recalled by De Witt.
  - Trustees of Columbia College to N-YHS, 1858 October 30 (Box 66, Folder 8)
    Formal signed and sealed contract for Columbia to host Lectures in Post-Graduate Instruction in the lecture hall of the new N-YHS building. OVERSIZE
  - Oliver Wendell Holmes to N-YHS, 1858 December 27 (Box 66, Folder 8)
    Decline of invitation to deliver lecture at N-YHS due to competing obligations.
  - Edward Everett to George H. Moore, 1858 December 29 (Box 66, Folder 8)
    Decline of invitation to repeat his lecture at N-YHS on Thomas Dowse, due to his opinion it is of local and personal interest only, and request to postpone lecture on Benjamin Franklin.
  - Fitz-Greene Halleck to George H. Moore, 1859 April 23 (Box 66, Folder 8)
    Acknowledgment of election as Corresponding Member of N-YHS.
  - Samuel F.B. Morse to Luther Bradish, 1859 May 28 (Box 66, Folder 8)
  - Hamilton Fish to George H. Moore, 1859 October 24 (Box 66, Folder 8)
    Letter accompanying donation of Dictionnaire Universel des Contemporaries, on behalf of M. Hachette and M. Vattermare.
  - Hamilton Fish to N-YHS, 1859 December 29 (Box 66, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence. 1860. Washington Irving Celebration, 1860 March-April (Box 66, Folder 9)